Prompt engineering was always a
little bit ridiculous,
but context is king.
You've got a window of at most a
million tokens to tell your LLM
everything it needs to know
about your business and what you
want your agent to accomplish.
If you think about what has to fit
in there, that's just not enough
space
to tackle complex tasks in the real
world.
If this is going to work,
we need to understand the building
blocks of context
in modern agentic applications and
have a framework to help us design
context with precision.
Let me show you what I mean.
Let's remember what an LLM even is.
It's a stateless box that
takes tokens as input.
You just think of them as little
pieces of words and gives us,
we'll say,
likely tokens as outputs.
It's important to kind of bring back
to this core thing.
It's very smart, does a lot of
really cool things.
These likely tokens are extremely
useful that come out, but it doesn't
remember anything.
We give it a bunch of text on the
input and text comes as the output
for the text mode.
When I said you have about a
million, that's for some models,
for some it might be 100,000,
something like that.
That could correspond to maybe 60
,000 words or 60 to 700,000 words,
somewhere in that.
The real problem with the LLM is
that it only knows what it's read on
the internet
and it can't do anything.
It just gives us tokens on the
output and we want to write agentic
applications
that take action and that know about
what's going on in the business.
So for our agents, we'll have some
kind of input.
That's probably a prompt from a
human at some point.
This agent now here is going
to make LLM calls and probably make
them iteratively.
It'll probably call an LLM more than
once
and it has the capability of calling
tools as well.
Those will let it actually take
action out in the world
and both the LLM call and the tool
call can be iterative.
This agent can have a workflow that
it kind of works out over time.
That can be running for a long time,
potentially, depending on the agent.
And that introduces some real
problems with context that we need
to solve.
All right, let's look now at kind of
a schema for thinking
about context.
What goes in the context window?
These tokens, this big prompt,
this string that we're submitting to
our LLM.
There are six things in here that I
want to lay out.
Let's first say, let's say here,
this is what I'm going to call user
message.
All right, now it's okay to think of
the chatbot interface,
the typical, you know,
Grok, Claude, ChatTPT kind of thing.
You type a thing and it says stuff
back.
And the you type a thing,
that stuff that you type,
that's the user message.
And that's probably going to be the
initial input to our agentic service
here,
some kind of user message.
That is not all.
There is always a system prompt.
In the chatbot applications,
you have some capability of
customizing that system prompt.
There's always system prompt, you're
not going to see.
But you can always tune that up a
little bit.
And that's going to tell things
like,
what's the personality of the LLM?
Like, what do you want it to be?
Do you want it to be a harsh and
demanding coach?
Do you want it to be sort of a
gentle and nurturing counselor?
You know, to kind of tell it what
you want.
Give it some guardrails.
Like, don't give me bomb -making
instructions.
Or be specific and detailed and cite
your sources in your output.
These are all sorts of things that
might go in a system prompt.
So it's just sort of up there.
You don't have to say all that stuff
over and over again.
It's always present.
We also have tools that we might
have access to.
The whole point here is that the
agent has access to tools.
And in its terminal step,
when it's done with its work,
that's a tool call.
That's causing an effect out in the
world.
So as a part of this context,
this text we're passing into the
LLM,
we have a description of the tools
that are available to us.
We also have resources.
Now this is a complex topic all
on its own.
Because the LLM only knows what it
reads on the internet,
we have to tell it things that are
specific to our business.
Like, hopefully all your Google Docs
are not shared publicly.
All of your Wiki articles and
internal support tickets and all
that kind of stuff.
You know, there really is private
data inside your enterprise
that is never going to be a part of
any LLM's training data set.
That's the resources.
So we have to somehow do a good job
of picking out which resources
belong inside this context window
into the submission to the LLM.
Those are things that are going to
be relevant to the user message.
Enough, but not too much.
We'll talk more about that in a bit.
You've also got the assistant
messages.
And assistant is, remember,
think of the chat model,
right?
You type stuff, it says stuff back.
It is your assistant.
So you give it a user message and
then it says something back.
That is the assistant message.
So as we iterate through,
and this is the case when you're
using a chat bot application,
you have actually a history of user
messages
and a history of assistant
messages that are accumulating
inside the context window.
So the longer the agent iterates,
the more space this stuff takes up.
Finally, you've got tool calls
and responses.
Call and response tools are calls
and results.
This is, as an agent is doing its
work, it may call tools as
intermediate steps,
not to terminate execution and have
its full result,
but to go do other things to help
build up context
to get to where it can be done with
its work.
So you may have a history of tool
calls and responses also as a part
of this.
These three components,
the history of tool calls,
user messages,
and assistant messages,
these are going to grow as execution
unfolds.
Resources, I'm drawing it as the
same size box as all the rest of
them.
It might not be the same size.
That might be a substantial number
of tokens there that are taken up by
resources.
System prompt, that's probably
reasonable, right?
Tools, that's probably going to be
limited.
But these other things can be a lot
of space.
You see, when you start to look at
what really goes into context,
you begin to understand even the big
models with a million tokens,
which again is not all of them.
That doesn't feel very roomy anymore
when you're thinking about
building complex, agentic
applications.
And it gets a little worse than
that.
It's not always the case that more
is better.
If you're using a model that has,
say, a 100,000 token context window,
it's a pretty consistent result at
this point that
maxing that out doesn't give you
your best results.
Somewhere in the 60 to 70 % range.
Again, let the research unfold on
this and let that number stabilize.
But kind of somewhere in the 60 to
70 % of the capacity of the context
window
is probably where you get your best
results.
So more isn't always better.
We actually do have to have tools
for engineering what goes in here.
And let's look at what that set of
tools is.
There's four things I want to cover.
First, there is the system prompt
itself.
Now, writing a good prompt is
important.
We need to get this right.
This is a thing that is kind of a
one -off for our agent.
And you want to nail it.
And there is a little bit of a
Goldilocks thing going on here.
We could, in this ditch over here,
be too vague.
We could say, I don't know,
do a good job
and go get all the stuff you need to
give me a good answer.
That's kind of stupid,
right?
That's not really going to work.
Over here, we could be too
prescriptive.
And for example, if you find
yourself in your system prompt
defining kind of if -then logic and
saying make sure you do this
and if this happens, you want to let
the LLM figure that out.
That's what it's going to be good
at.
So don't do that.
Don't do that.
You want to be in the middle where
you define outcomes,
you define maybe broad approaches to
things.
And I realize this is itself
somewhat vague.
But it's a balance that you're going
to have to learn how to strike.
And that is sort of the art of
prompt engineering
is making sure that you're not too
prescriptive, not too vague.
So get the system prompt right.
Engineer that thing.
That's something you actually have
to pay attention to.
What's next?
Tools.
Pretty simple here.
You just want to make sure your tool
descriptions are specific and
detailed.
You never want them to be too long.
More is not always better.
But you want them to really nail
down what does this tool do.
You want the LLM to be able to,
as it were, understand what that
thing is for.
So you want to be specific.
And you want to include a schema.
We have to know what goes into that
tool, what comes out of that tool.
That's important because the LLM
will need to know that it has all
the right inputs
to be able to conclude that it can
call the tool.
And it's going to need to know what
it gets out of the tool
because that may be an input to a
next step of, say, a resource it
needs to go get
or something like that.
So full schemas, specific,
precise tool descriptions.
OK, what's next?
We've got data retrieval.
And this really goes right here to
resources.
This is what we're talking about.
Now, the initial approach when folks
just started trying to use LLMs
in an enterprise context was the
Retrieval Augmented Generation
Approach, or RAG,
where we've got a vector database.
We index any document we think we
might need to have involved in a
lookup.
And now when I've got a user
message, I'll take that user message
and use it in the vector database to
go retrieve any documents I think
are related,
put them into the context,
and away I go.
And that's good for an information
search, chatbot kind of thing.
It worked.
And that may well still be a part of
your stack.
And I'm not here to tell you that
you're old fashioned
or behind the times or anything.
But RAG by itself is not very
precise context engineering on a go
-forward basis.
There's more we can do to
economically use the context window
that we've got.
So now we've got MCP, the Model
Context Protocol,
and its disclosure of resources that
can be queried.
Those resources, like tools,
are described with text
and maybe with parameters that can
be involved in a query
if they're queryable resources.
And so those descriptions can go
into the context window of one call.
And a subsequent call,
if you ask the LLM, can say,
hey, you know what, I need you to go
query this resource.
That can even be, there's this
little arrow here
where this agent is making multiple
iterative calls.
One of those calls could be simply
to ask,
based on this user message,
which resources should I go
retrieve?
And the LLM will tell you,
based on its conclusion,
you go get those resources.
Now you've got a big string.
You can dump that into the resources
section
of your next context window for your
next call
as the agent moves along.
There are other things we can do to
make economical use of this,
like say, if you've got a user
record that could be kind of long,
maybe just give it a user ID.
And if there's a resource or a tool
or something
that clearly can turn that user ID
into a full record
on a subsequent call, you can get
the model to ask you.
You can prompt it to ask you if it
needs more detail on that user,
call this tool or ask for this
resource.
So there are all kinds of things we
can do here
to just be economical with our
data that we have in here.
Rather than anything that might
sound like it's related,
we can just sort of describe what's
available
and use prompting to have the model
tell us
what we need to go get and include.
Finally, we've got the long horizon
thinking.
And this is for an agent that we
know
is going to be really iterating for
a long time.
We suspect that it might need to
make a bunch of calls.
And these things that grow as the
agent's runtime increases,
those are going to be our enemy.
And so there are some things that we
can do
to help keep those small,
or at least within the context
window of any given call.
First is compaction.
One thing LLMs are incredible at is
summarizing text.
If I've got some resource I've
retrieved on a previous call
and it's, you know, 50,000 tokens or
something,
a really big thing, you know,
I don't want to have all of that in
my next call.
So I could use a single LLM call
with my own prompt
to say, please summarize this in 500
words.
And now I've got that compacted
summary
that goes in as a resource.
That can often give you pretty good
results.
Next is memory.
Memory is literally just,
it's going to be a little key value
store
hanging off to the side here.
And that will let me at one point in
my agent's execution
take some resource, some
intermediate result,
maybe an assistant message
that itself could be somewhat
lengthy.
Maybe it's some kind of structured
data.
Maybe it's like a bunch of JSON or
CSV
or who knows what's going on
with this crazy agent you're
writing.
And we can put that in here under a
certain key
and on a subsequent step when we
need it,
retrieve it out of that memory.
So it's conceptually like what
happens
with retrieving resources from an
MCP server,
but it really is memory that's local
to our agent
and that we get to use to store that
stuff.
You don't have much space here.
You might need to put certain things
over here
where this space is relatively
cheap.
Finally, we have, I'm just going to
say,
additional agents.
Composition.
I can take my one big agent,
and I think this is a thing that is
just likely to happen
as you're building an agentic
application.
Tell me if this has ever happened
when you're building a microservice
and it starts to get a little
complex
and you realize it's a little bit of
its own
little mini monolith
and you have to split it into
pieces.
This is what it's like to build
software.
When you're writing an agent,
it's probably going to end up
decomposing
into multiple agents.
Let's say one of the resources
you've got
is your documentation site
or your wiki or something like that,
and you've got some kind of complex
search logic
that's doing a lot of iteration.
Man, that's just its own agent.
So split that off,
and now this agent can ask that
agent,
I've got this text.
I'd like to know what documents
from your system look relevant.
And now rather than just a text
search
on that document store,
you can have an agent
that does some kind of thoughtful
sorting through things and
prioritizing
and back and forth with an LLM
to do a good job of giving you
some concise summary of what comes
from that store.
So be ready to take little chunks
of agentic functionality in your
agent
that really could live on their own
and make them their own thing.
So there you go.
We've got a schema for context,
the user message, system prompt,
whatever resources we can cobble
together,
listing of the tools,
the assistant messages we get
from our back and forth with the
agent,
and of course a record of the tools
that we've called.
That's a lot.
That's all got to fit
into the LLM's context window,
and those aren't getting a lot
bigger.
So we have these tools,
engineer your system prompt,
describe your tools well,
retrieve data intelligently,
use this resources section wisely,
and for long horizon iterative
execution,
you've got these tools available to
you.
Context engineering is the present
and future of agentic AI
development.
I encourage you to put these tools
into practice.
And as always,
you're building something with this,
let me know in the comments.
And if this is work you're doing,
especially if you work with
streaming data,
the company I work for,
Confluent, has got some really cool
stuff
to help with this.
We've got a new thing called
Confluent Intelligence
that helps solve some of these
problems,
particularly for agents
that work with streaming data.
So if that's interesting,
check it out.
There's a link and a promo code
in the description
that'll let you get started
trying that for free.
Check it out.
Thanks.